<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>MelonadeM&#x27;s Blog</title>
    <link href="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://melonadem.github.io/blog" />
    <updated>2022-01-06T16:11:26+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Mel</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://melonadem.github.io/blog</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Swapping Batteries Out: The Hard Way (Part 1)</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/swapping-batteries-out-the-hard-way-part-1/"/>
        <id>https://melonadem.github.io/blog/swapping-batteries-out-the-hard-way-part-1/</id>
            <category term="synths"/>
            <category term="rackmount"/>
            <category term="mels-workshop"/>
            <category term="90s"/>

        <updated>2022-01-06T16:11:26+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4/s4-takenapartsolder.jpg" alt="S4 Taken Apart with Soldering Equipment" />
                    <p>Swapping a battery out is easy if it's designed to be easy to access and replace, like you've (and I've) seen on the last post where I did it en masse with my synths. It's an entirely different world, however, when that is not the case, i.e. it's hard to access and/or replace. What can you do, in that case? Well...</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4/s4-takenapartsolder.jpg" alt="S4 Taken Apart with Soldering Equipment" />
                <p>Swapping a battery out is easy if it's designed to be easy to access and replace, like you've (and I've) seen on the last post where I did it en masse with my synths. It's an entirely different world, however, when that is not the case, i.e. it's hard to access and/or replace. What can you do, in that case? Well...</p>

<h2>Enter The Hard Way</h2>
<p>It's often more expensive to buy a holder and solder that in, placing the battery separately, compared to just soldering in a battery type and going on your merry way to ship your product. Some companies understood this, and still decided to go for the holder method, as they knew those synthesizers would still be used years on (and, a lot of them are!). Roland, Korg and Yamaha were usually good about this, and if they weren't, a solder job is usually easy... that is, unless you're Alesis.</p>
<p>Alesis was not always known for synthesizers or any kind of sounds. They started off producing and building various PA equipment on the cheap. However, by the late 80s, they have branched out into other domains, notably in the drums department with their HR-16 drum machines, which were popular.</p>
<p>The HR-16's... used a weird battery type. Instead of a coin cell, like a typical CR2032, they opted for a big, bulky 3.6v battery that resembles a D cell more than anything, I'm not even sure if it is a D cell. Regardless, it served the same purpose as other batteries in products of this time: Provide power to a SRAM chip and preserve user settings or patterns.</p>
<p>By the 90s, Alesis shifted from those bulky batteries to more conventional 3V Lithium coin cell batteries. However, instead of using something more traditional, like a CR2032, they went with a BR2325 battery, and it was attached with tabs to the synths themselves. Giving credit where it's due, many Alesis products used this battery type: From SR-16s to Quadrasynths, to DM5s and DM-PROs.</p>
<p>In actuality, the BR2325 is not too dissimilar to the CR2032, both are Li-Ion batteries, both provide 3 volts of power, really the only difference is in its chemical build. CR batteries are more commonly available, but the BRs are able to sustain higher temperatures for longer. Regardless, what this means is, given the right holder, you can totally use a CR2032 in those synths, and users <em>have </em>done so in the past with their SR-16's. I might be the first example of doing this with a Quadrasynth S4 (and eventually a QSR too)</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--wide" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4//alesis-s4.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4//responsive/alesis-s4-xs.jpg 300w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4//responsive/alesis-s4-sm.jpg 480w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4//responsive/alesis-s4-md.jpg 768w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4//responsive/alesis-s4-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4//responsive/alesis-s4-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4//responsive/alesis-s4-2xl.jpg 1600w"  alt="The synth in question, before surgical procedure" width="4032" height="829">
<figcaption >The quiant Alesis S4, months before being out of function (replaced by QSR), also months before lobotomy.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>For an early 1994 synth, it was quite capable - 64 total voices, a maximum of 4 could make up one program, and up to 16 of those could be played at once in a mix. While it had a diverse amount of sounds, it didn't compare to the contemporaries of the time like Roland's JV synths, or even Korg's Ai2 synths (the 01/W and derivatives) which released before the Quadrasynth. It still saw some success, enough to convince Alesis to keep going with it, and true to Alesis's track record, it was fairly inexpensive (and compact when talking about the S4).</p>
<p>Regardless, it and many other Alesis products of this era used the same BR2325 batteries, and getting to the battery requires disassembling the entire synth completely. Remove the top, the bottom, the side ears... disconnect the front panel (which I would have wanted to do anyway, this S4 in particular has some really non-functioning buttons and knobs, hoping some contact cleaner will solve the issue. This'll all be concluded in part 2)</p>
<p>Anyway, the synth was taken fully apart, and I could finally get to the battery. This was my first time soldering, and honestly it shows cause I snipped the dang thing off and then removed the legs, and it wasn't a particularly clean job. I even scratched a bit of the PCB, but no problem, it'll be covered up by the holder.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4/s4-battery-layout.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4/responsive/s4-battery-layout-xs.jpg 300w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4/responsive/s4-battery-layout-sm.jpg 480w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4/responsive/s4-battery-layout-md.jpg 768w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4/responsive/s4-battery-layout-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4/responsive/s4-battery-layout-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/4/responsive/s4-battery-layout-2xl.jpg 1600w"  alt="Layout of the battery in the S4" width="838" height="664">
<figcaption >The BR2325 has 3 terminals, two positive (shown on the left hand side, with one being unused) and one negative (on the right hand side)</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The battery layout was a bit of a brain-scratcher, but it turns out some Alesis products use the other pin (unused here) for the positive connection. I haven't encountered a situation where both are going to be used at the same time, so this pin can just remain unconnected. There are no traces leading through, or to it, so it should be fine. Here's hoping.</p>
<p>Either way - the battery holder will have to be connected slightly diagonally, but that should be fine. It should fit just fine, as a CR2032 is a smaller diameter than BR2325.</p>
<p>CR/BR denotes the battery chemicals, 20/23 denote the diameter in millimeters/mm, 32/25 denote the thickness in tenths of millimeters, so a CR2032 is a CR-type battery with a 20mm diameter and a 3.2mm thickness, BR2325 is a BR-type battery with a 23mm diameter and a 2.5mm thickness.</p>
<h2>Planning for the Future</h2>
<p>I could just have ordered an identical, brand-new replacement, but the prices on <em>those </em>are extraordinarily high - £14 for <em>one </em>god-damned battery, with another £15 for postage. That is absurd, I got a CR2032 holder for... £2, with free shipping, and I have spare CR2032 batteries that are brand new.</p>
<p>Moreso, using a holder will make it easier to change out the battery when it goes bad again. Sure, by then, maybe an IC will have failed, rendering the synth useless, or if not an IC, a capacitor somewhere, whose juices will have corroded some important traces, meaning it needs a trip to the solder doctor somewhere. I could do that, but I'm not sure if a new owner would bother doing so, and might just throw it away.</p>
<p>...Perhaps it's time we start preserving the Quadrasynth line beyond restoring the original boxes or keyboards, by making a softsynth version of some kind. Only time can tell, but I wish I knew DSP programming and how to work with ICs, dumping ROM data and doing <em>something </em>with it...</p>
<p>Either way, in part 2 I'm going to place the new holder, repair the front panel, put it all back together and pray that it works. If it does, then it's going to go to a friend overseas. If it doesn't, well it was still worth a shot, and now that I have this soldering equipment, I might try to create something using it. Only time can tell.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Buying an old synth? Replace the batteries ASAP.</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/buying-an-old-synth-replace-the-batteries-asap/"/>
        <id>https://melonadem.github.io/blog/buying-an-old-synth-replace-the-batteries-asap/</id>
            <category term="synths"/>
            <category term="rackmount"/>
            <category term="mels-workshop"/>
            <category term="90s"/>

        <updated>2021-10-22T18:17:50+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/featuredimage.png" alt="Featured image." />
                    <p>Don't delay, old batteries can eventually start leaking out and will ruin your synths, especially older ones. Replacing them, while usually not the hardest task, can be oddly challenging at times. Let's talk about the what, the why, and the how.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/featuredimage.png" alt="Featured image." />
                <p>Don't delay, old batteries can eventually start leaking out and will ruin your synths, especially older ones. Replacing them, while usually not the hardest task, can be oddly challenging at times. Let's talk about the what, the why, and the how.</p>
<hr>
<h2>Batteries?!</h2>
<p>Old synthesizers often used volatile memory to store sound information that's modified by the user, but a common problem with doing this is that you would lose that data upon powering off the device. You could use non-volatile storage, something like cassette tape, or a hard disk, but those were often slow and clumsy, compared to memory.</p>
<p>Enter batteries. This is a very clever solution - store it in a memory chip, but keep the memory chip powered at all times via a coin-cell battery. This way, the user can have the speed of blazing-fast RAM of the time, combined with the convenience of patch storage. This was the leading way to store programs, patches, performances and what-have-you on a ton of older workstations and synthesizers, with the other prominent way being floppy disks - remember those? 💾</p>
<p>In short, batteries keep supplying power to where you would store your sound programs and patches, even when powered off, so you can access them at any point. Think of it like old SNES and Gameboy games doing save storage.</p>
<p>Obviously those won't last forever. You have to eventually open up your prized synth or game, and replace the battery, losing all of your hard work (hopefully you have it backed up!). Tangential, but batteries could also be used for a real-time clock, and that's why you have some copies of Pokémon games that don't have a working clock.</p>
<p>Sure, you can live without saving or storage, but another, much bigger problem is leakage. Batteries build up gases inside that, if potent enough, can puncture through the metal casing. This doesn't normally occur if the device is actively used from manufacturing date, however we all know that doesn't really ever happen, synth and game alike. Therefore, you can totally end up with acid buildup, or worse, corrosion. So... if it's dead, or if it's old, why not just replace it?</p>
<h2>Replacing a battery</h2>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/solderedbattery.png" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/solderedbattery-xs.png 300w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/solderedbattery-sm.png 480w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/solderedbattery-md.png 768w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/solderedbattery-lg.png 1024w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/solderedbattery-xl.png 1360w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/solderedbattery-2xl.png 1600w"  alt="Soldered battery" width="2528" height="1422">
<figcaption >If your battery looks like this, it is soldered!</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>This process can be either simple enough for anyone with a screwdriver to do, or requires a soldering iron (if it's soldered).</p>
<p>I'm focusing on the former, as I don't have a soldering iron <em>yet </em>(I will have to use one for my QSR and S4 synths, more on that some other time).</p>
<p>Open up your synth, making sure it's not connected to power or anything, and look around and find where the battery is located. It should be pretty obvious where it is (if not, look for a coin-shaped object encased in some plastic holding it down), make note of what type of battery it is (CR2032s are common in synths, not so much in games), and either order or go out to buy a replacement.</p>
<p>Chances are you'll get them in bulk - perfect if you're like me and have multiple synths!</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--wide" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/holder-battery.png" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/holder-battery-xs.png 300w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/holder-battery-sm.png 480w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/holder-battery-md.png 768w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/holder-battery-lg.png 1024w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/holder-battery-xl.png 1360w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/holder-battery-2xl.png 1600w"  alt="Battery in a holder" width="1682" height="946">
<figcaption >If your battery looks (somewhat) like this, it's in a holder. Simply push forward then pull up, and it'll get out with ease!</figcaption>
</figure>
<p> </p>
<p>After doing this, make sure you dispose of the old battery properly, do <em>not </em>just throw it in a bin! You should have some services for recycling batteries around wherever you live.</p>
<h2>Doing it in bulk</h2>
<p>...is exhausting as hell.</p>
<p>You should do this as soon as you get something new, because doing it in bulk, even if you're talking 4 or 5 devices at most, is tiring. You have to open each synth up, look for the battery, either pop it out and pop a new one in, or replace it via soldering, then screw it back on, THEN make sure it still works (it most likely will).</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/u220-test.png" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/u220-test-xs.png 300w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/u220-test-sm.png 480w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/u220-test-md.png 768w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/u220-test-lg.png 1024w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/u220-test-xl.png 1360w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/u220-test-2xl.png 1600w"  alt="U220 patch memory test (successful)" width="3208" height="1804">
<figcaption >U220 with a recently replaced battery - it's alive!</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>That alone can take around 15 minutes just for a single unit, and it'll create a big mess in your studio.</p>
<p>It is worth doing it if you haven't been able to before, but it is more worth doing it as your synths come (or go, if you're planning to sell any and haven't recently done this). Possibly, it'll take even more if you have to solder, but I'm not qualified to have a say yet.</p>
<p>The outcome of doing it in bulk though is very rewarding, and it also allows you to redo your cabling if it's a mess like mine is. Meh, mine's still not great, haha...</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--wide" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/rack-final.png" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/rack-final-xs.png 300w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/rack-final-sm.png 480w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/rack-final-md.png 768w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/rack-final-lg.png 1024w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/rack-final-xl.png 1360w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/3/responsive/rack-final-2xl.png 1600w"  alt="Final result of doing this procedure in bulk" width="4032" height="2268">
<figcaption >Happily living together, aye?</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>A little tidbit before I go - the battery in the thumbnail was one of four I replaced today, it was the U220 one. It's also the oldest synth I have, having been released in 1989, so that checks out I suppose.</p>
<p>Anywho, thanks for reading - see you soon.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Simmering thoughts on Dread</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/simmering-thoughts-on-dread/"/>
        <id>https://melonadem.github.io/blog/simmering-thoughts-on-dread/</id>
            <category term="video-game"/>
            <category term="thoughts-on"/>
            <category term="switch"/>
            <category term="metroid"/>

        <updated>2021-10-22T18:18:14+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/2/featuredimg.png" alt="Simmering thoughts on Dread Featured Image" />
                    This is one of the very few times where I bought a game as it was newly-released, and also the ONLY case so far where I bought an entire new console to play it on (It's a Switch exclusive, and I really did not want&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/2/featuredimg.png" alt="Simmering thoughts on Dread Featured Image" />
                <p>This is one of the very few times where I bought a game as it was newly-released, and also the ONLY case so far where I bought an entire new console to play it on (It's a Switch exclusive, and I really did not want to pirate it or emulate it - I'm glad I didn't)</p>
<p>Was it worth it? Absolutely. I'm going to elaborate on why, but before that, if it's not obvious already: <strong>SPOILERS AHEAD!</strong> If you haven't played this yet, and have any kind of interest to, <em>please, please play it first.</em></p>
<h2>Before Dread</h2>
<p>I already considered myself a Metroid fan, long before Dread was announced. I started with Super, and was content with playing through that alone a long time ago. It's left an impression on me, an excellent game that uses design and detailing to make it not only an immersive experience, but also one that doesn't leave you lost, without ever being told where to go. There's only one instance I recall where I had to look for a bit of help, and that's honestly fine.</p>
<p>After Dread got announced, and particularly after hearing so much about it being a great title, I decided I would bite the bullet, all while experiencing Zero Mission and Fusion for the first time. I love those games a lot, too. Sure, they're more linear than Super, and you <em>are </em>told where to go quite often, but that's fine by me. </p>
<p>Especially after playing those two games, back to back, it revalidated my love for the series, and was the single most deciding factor for me buying not only a whole-ass Switch (OLED model too), but a copy of Metroid Dread, too.</p>
<p>Firstly - the Switch is fantastic, so far. I really, really enjoy that I can use it both portably and as a console. I'm looking forward to check out its library (I've already bought Mario Odyssey, and will likely buy BotW at some point, too). I've heard it's gotten panned for its faulty controllers (Joycon drift), and honestly, yeah. That should be fixed, if it wasn't already. C'mon, Nintendo (and Sony, you too - apparently your PS5 controllers also have drifting - what's the matter with these issues?)</p>
<hr>
<h2>First Impressions</h2>
<p>I set the Switch up, spent a bit of time getting familiar with it, by virtue of playing Yoshi's Island (which, frankly, isn't a fun game upon replaying it). Once I've had enough of Yoshi, I booted Dread up. Man, was I glad I did so, cause what followed was an extremely fun time.</p>
<p>I <em>did </em>spoil myself on the first 40 minutes or so, by virtue of watching <a href="https://www.twitch.tv/hypercole64">Cole</a> play through it blind. I decided I wouldn't want to spoil myself any further after that point, and decided to drop the money on the console + game, as stated before.</p>
<p>But... even then, playing it for <em>myself </em>was such a surreal experience. The game looked great, it sounded great, it <em>played </em>great. I was enjoying myself playing a brand-new game, the last time that happened was with Sonic Mania, an excellent game in its own right.</p>
<p>I found the EMMI terrifying, as would anyone else, but also interesting. The first one being crippled, and more or less an excuse to show you both what an EMMI is, how you can get rid of it, and the area EMMI live in (also explained by Adam, to be fair), it's a facet of good, albeit a bit forceful design. This particular first one being crippled to hell and beyond definitely helped alleviate the stress that later ones came with, in hindsight.</p>
<p>Defeating it felt good, and, if I'm remembering correctly, gave you a power up that lets you explore more of the area you're currently in, and get into new areas, too.</p>
<p><em>I just realized </em>I completely skimmed over the intro - Samus gets into a fight with some sort of Chozo?, and she loses her powerups like that. We... have no idea what happened, and neither does she, apparently. I suppose we'll find out later, and find out later we shall.</p>
<hr>
<h2>Meat of the Game</h2>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/2/dread1.png" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/2/responsive/dread1-xs.png 300w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/2/responsive/dread1-sm.png 480w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/2/responsive/dread1-md.png 768w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/2/responsive/dread1-lg.png 1024w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/2/responsive/dread1-xl.png 1360w ,https://melonadem.github.io/blog/media/posts/2/responsive/dread1-2xl.png 1600w"  alt="Image capture of Metroid Dread" width="1280" height="720"></figure>
<p>Honestly you probably don't need me to tell you this - it plays like a Metroid game. The new counter mechanic (to me, as I haven't played Samus Returns) is implemented well, I like that you're encouraged to master it as countering then killing an enemy nets you more health/missiles than a regular kill would. You also get upgrades not really seen in previous Metroid games, as is usually the case with new games, and they work well enough.</p>
<p>There's new types of doors, too, ones that require different beams, for one. I honestly think this could've been executed better. I don't like opening grapple beam doors, I don't like using the grapple beam period honestly. But aside from that, we have a new type of morph ball, one that destroys blocks in a + pattern, and can also get you across pitfall blocks.</p>
<p>A lot more devious setups using both old and new powerups are also located all across the game, especially speed booster puzzles - This game loves putting speed booster blocks in unconventional spots, and usually not for a huge reward, just missiles. In a sense, it makes it purely optional, as players playing casually <em>will </em>have health, missiles and whatnot required to beat the game, while people going for 100% will want to learn the setups and how to get them quickly... but, honestly, as a more casual player, that defeats the purpose for me. Why go for this puzzle/setup when the reward is just a few missiles? Sure, it's <em>nice, </em>but more energy is always more appreciated by me. Not to mention, puzzles that don't reveal what the reward is. There was a very devious speed booster puzzle, I barely got it while hurting my thumbs, and the reward was a measly pack of two missiles. Seriously?</p>
<p>I 100%'d the first area of the game, Artaria, and I also 100%'d the last area, as it only had 3 items or so. Other areas varied between 50%-ish to 95%, and it was enough to get me 86% items upon clearing. I can always go back to 100% it, but I would rather do it on a new save and also get a faster time to boot, as 12 hours isn't that nice, but... that's for the next section, I believe.</p>
<p>Gripe aside, I did enjoy the puzzles the game threw at you, there was no shortage of "A-ha!" moments, where a previously seemingly-impossible puzzle becomes possible. For one of those, <a href="https://twitter.com/_melonadem/status/1450173574820470787">I had to ask for help on Twitter</a>, but I feel that's natural with Metroidvanias, to an extent. I appreciate that MOST things are completable by yourself with enough dedication and some thought, I just wish everything was, haha.</p>
<p>To help offset that, at least, there's plenty of instances where sequence-breaking is possible, not for big items but the smaller ones? It's chock full of them, and I have a feeling a lot of them were intentional, too. This ain't Mercury Steam's first rodeo at a Metroid game, anyhow, it's their second, and they clearly have a knack for this design philosophy, as they quite literally nailed it well here.</p>
<p>Another thing I enjoyed seeing is plenty of recharge stations scattered throughout the map. They weren't bundled with save rooms or anything, and there were various kinda: energy, ammo, and total stations. Energy and Ammo are self-explanatory, total would recharge/refill both types. Teleporters, too. Makes for quick backtracking, barring the load times. I like how after you discover all teleporters, you can go to any teleporter, from any teleporter, similar to the Symphony of the Night teleportation, if I'm remembering right.</p>
<p>Story wise, you're trying to return to your ship, and leave the planet. However, as you try to dwelve your way up to your ship, you're encountering more EMMI (which restore some of your abilities), finding Chozo statues (obtaining suits, beams and whatnot), and fighting bosses while trying to get out of here, essentially.</p>
<p>Around the middle of the game, you encounter an actual Chozo?, which tries to help you out by disabling the remaining EMMI, but he gets killed by a new faction of enemies, the Mawkins. They're like Chozo, from what I can recall, but trying to resurrect Metroids, as it was their sign of greatness. You, as Samus Aran, are the only remaining being with Metroid DNA, and the guy at the beginning of the game wants to extract it from you. Essentially you were lured to ZDR via footage from an X parasite roaming around the planet, and Raven Beak (the bad guy from the intro) wants to harvest your DNA to once again create Metroids.</p>
<p>As you blow up some form of research facility?, a ton of X parasites break out, infecting... everything on the planet, pretty much. The Chozo that helped you (that was dead) is revived, and turns the EMMI back on, basically you have to get away from them like you have been doing so far.</p>
<p>One thing I kinda dislike, though, is how the EMMI become less and less relevant as the game reaches the end. The last one you don't even fight, you just... well, we shall get to that later. The last set of them are quickly defeated, and I don't know, they just stop being a constant threat when they were set up to be THE thing to be most fearful of at the intro. Maybe it's you becoming strong and that's a way the game uses to signify that, but still. It's at least better than the SA-X from Fusion in terms of terror and tension.</p>
<p>The X parasites act the same as they have in Fusion, where you can absorb them (and where they can mutate into enemies, fuse and whatnot). I actually don't quite understand <em>why </em>they're here, but it doesn't matter too much, I guess.</p>
<hr>
<h2>All Things Must Come to an End</h2>
<p>While I have been somewhat critical here, it's purely because I love the series - despite those few flaws, I very much enjoyed myself. Let's talk about the ending parts.</p>
<p>During the interlude between Super Metroid and Metroid Fusion, Samus went back on SR388 and got infected with the X parasite, we all know that. She got a specially-developed Metroid DNA vaccine that immediately cured her, but as a result she's also pretty much THE only living thing that contains any trace of a metroid. The BSL labs crashed on to SR388, blowing the planet up, eliminating the metroids that they were producing.</p>
<p>The mawkins do not take kindly to this either - again, they saw metroids as THEIR magnum opus, as things that should rule every corner of the galaxy. You fight them a couple times throughout the game, either as actual mawkins or X-parasite infected ones that also do wacky crap.</p>
<p>As you progress into Hanubia, you're... noticing something weird about yourself. You can sporadically and unpredictably start to suck energy out of anything living or not, and you're doing that with the last EMMI, too, just for good measure. It'd seem like Raven Beak was awakening the Metroid DNA within you, and well he did succeed. During your confrontation with him, it seems like every odd is stacked against you, but as things hit their most dire point... your powers awaken.</p>
<p>Yes. Samus Aran turns into an actual Metroid. Not LITERALLY, but in spirit. Her suit even gains a very cool metroid theming and she's become very overpowered. There's a difference between her and actual Metroids, likely because this one would have a whole functioning cerebral system, while "actual" Metroids mindlessly hunt prey down. This is further embelished by Adam telling Samus "don't", when trying to operate the ship in her Metroid form.</p>
<p>Now, one confusing thing... earlier in the game, we see that the Chozo dude has been infected with the X parasite, and starts re-enabling the EMMI to give Samus more to deal with, which makes sense? I guess? But in the ending, he's there, and... the parasite turns Samus back to normal? Does the X know it's powerless against Samus, and offers to help instead? It's weird and kind of confusing. We already do know that the X parasites clearly possess some form of intelligence, as seen in Fusion, and something similar DOES happen there, where the SA-X merges with you and gives you a proper ice-beam, for one.</p>
<p>It's also unclear to me what the heck that last Adam conversation, right before the boss, was really about. Why did Adam start going about how "his" plan worked? Obviously it had to be hijacked to some extent by Raven Beak, but did he also do that for every other Adam conversation? Did he only do it for the bit where "his plan worked"? It's confusing, and while a Metroid game is not purely for the plot I still think it could have been handled a bit better, or given some explanation.</p>
<p>Another thing... there's no epilogue. Just, your ship cruises off into the depths of space, leaving you with a clear time and a "See you next mission!"</p>
<hr>
<h2>Closing Thoughts</h2>
<p>I hope this game does well financially. I hope it shows Nintendo that Metroid is a popular franchise worth developing games for, and while I do not hope they pump out games yearly, like Capcom would with Mega Man in the early 90s, I hope it's something that occurs each new console generation.</p>
<p>In terms of a rating, god, it's hard to say, really - maybe 8.5/10?? I'm not a critic with any significance, especially not for games, so take it with a grain of salt.</p>
<p><strong>Graphics: 8/10</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Looks great, albeit jagged in some places, and oddly lower-res even docked. Frame drops are rare, it maintains a smooth 60fps in most cases.</li>
<li>Handheld it looks great and not downscaled at all, at least to the naked eye.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sound: 9/10</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The music isn't exactly memorable, but it helps set up the mood and atmosphere for any particular scene. Underwater music is as serene as usual for Metroid, other areas have a motif of some sort, "safe" rooms have a clear release of tension, while EMMI zones are rightfully unnerving to travel in, with being spotted/heard evolving the music and making it even more chaotic.</li>
<li>The sound design is fantastic, 10/10 for it alone, a TON of instances where the rumble helps sell this even more.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Gameplay: 8/10</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>It feels good to play. While I have a few quirks with the controls, they're ultimately nothing too major. Only time it got legitimately worse than that is when I was hunting for items and had to activate my speed booster, which was awkward to do and kinda painful in the worst of worst cases.</li>
<li>The game is designed well for 90% of it, in most cases what was my fault WAS my fault, however the 10% was bosses that felt a bit too difficult for my liking, and the one part where Artaria is frozen over, and had to ask someone about how to progress from there. Turns out, I missed a block that was breakable in a pretty obvious spot.</li>
</ul>
<p>Yeah, that'll do.</p>
<p>See you next post!</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Hello world!</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://melonadem.github.io/blog/hello-world/"/>
        <id>https://melonadem.github.io/blog/hello-world/</id>

        <updated>2021-10-15T19:37:28+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is more of a test post, I'm trying to see if I can pull off a simple blog for general long-winded musings and thoughts, would be a better deal than trying to use TwitLonger, haha. Anyway! We shall see how well it works out.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This is more of a test post, I'm trying to see if I can pull off a simple blog for general long-winded musings and thoughts, would be a better deal than trying to use TwitLonger, haha.</p>
<p>Anyway! We shall see how well it works out.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
